So wouldn't it be amazing if our phones
ألن يكون رائعاً لو أن هواتفنا
could see the world in the same way that we do,
بإمكانها رؤية العالم بالطريقة التي نراها نحن ،
as we're walking around being able
وعندما نتجوّل نكون قادرين على
to point a phone at anything,
توجيه هاتفنا نحو أي شيء ،
and then have it actually recognize images and objects
وتكون قادرةً على التعرف إلى صور وأجسام
like the human brain, and then be able to pull in information
مثلما يفعل المخ البشري ، ومن ثم تستطيع تحميل معلومات
from an almost infinite library of knowledge
من مكتبةٍ لا متناهيةٍ تقريباً من المعلومات
and experiences and ideas.
والخبرات والأفكار.
Well, traditionally that was seen as science fiction,
حسناً ، في العادة كان هذا يعتبر من الخيال العلمي ،
but now we've moved to a world
ولكننا الآن أصبحنا في عالمٍ
where actually this has become possible.
حيث يكون ذلك ممكناً.
So the best way of explaining it is to just show it.
والطريقة الأمثل لتوضيح ذلك هو بعرضه مباشرةً.
What you can see over here is Tamara,
ومن تشاهدونها هنا هي تمارا ،
who is holding my phone that's now plugged in.
وهي تحمل هاتفي وهو متصلٌ الآن.
So let me start with this.
لنبدأ بهذا.
What we have here is a painting
مالدينا هنا هي لوحة
of the great poet Rabbie Burns,
للشاعر العظيم رابي بيرنز ،
and it's just a normal image,
وهي صورةٌ عادية ،
but if we now switch inputs over to the phone,
ولكن الآن إذا نظرنا من خلال الهاتف ،
running our technology, you can see
والذي يُشغلُ تقنيّتنا ، بإمكانكم مشاهدة
effectively what Tamara's seeing on the screen,
ما تراهُ تمارا فعلياً من خلال الشاشة ،
and when she points at this image,
وعندما توجه تمارا الشاشة إلى الصورة ،
something magical happens.
يحدثُ شيءٌ خارق.
(Laughter) (Bagpipes)
(ضحك) (موسيقى مزمار)
(Bagpipes) (Applause)
(موسيقى مزمار) (تصفيق)
(Bagpipes)
(موسيقى مزمار)
Voice: Now simmer blinks on flowery braes ...
صوت: الآن الوهج يومض في المنحدرات الزهرية ...
Matt Mills: Now, what's great about this is,
مات ميلز: الآن ، الجيد في هذا ،
there's no trickery here.
أنه لا توجد أية خدع.
There's nothing done to this image.
لم يتم عمل أي شىء لهذه الصورة.
And what's great about this is the technology's
والشيء الرآئع خلف ذلك هو التقنية
actually allowing the phone to start to see and understand
المستخدمة التي تسمح للهاتف بالمشاهدة والتحليل
much like how the human brain does.
مثلما يفعل المخ البشري.
Not only that, but as I move the object around,
ليس هذا وحسب ، بل كلما حرّكت الجسم ،
it's going to track it and overlay that content seamlessly.
سيقوم الهاتف بتتبعه ووضع المحتوى عليه بكل سلاسة.
Again, the thing that's incredible about this is
ومرةً أُخرى ، الشيء المذهل في ذلك
this is how advanced these devices have become.
هو الدرجة التي وصلت إليها هذه الأجهزة من التطور.
All the processing to do that was actually done
فكل المعالجات الضرورية تتم فعلياً
on the device itself.
في الجهاز نفسه.
Now, this has applications everywhere,
والآن ، لهذا تطبيقاتٌ متعددة في كل مكان ،
whether in things like art in museums, like you just saw,
سواءً في المتاحف الفنية ، كما رأيتم ،
or in the world of, say, advertising, or print journalism.
أو في عالم ، الإعلانات ، أو الصحافة المطبوعة.
So a newspaper becomes out of date as soon as it's printed.
إذ أن الصُحُف تصبح قديمةً بمجرّد طباعتها.
And here is this morning's newspaper,
وهنا صحيفة صدرت صباح اليوم ،
and we have some Wimbledon news, which is great.
ولدينا بعض أخبار ويمبلدون ، وهذا جيد.
Now what we can do is point at the front of the newspaper
والآن نستطيع أن نوجه الهاتف إلى واجهة الصحيفة
and immediately get the bulletin.
ونستطيع الحصول على الأخبار المباشرة.
Voice: ... To the grass, and it's very important that you adapt
صوت: ... إلى العشب ، ومن المهم جداً أن تتكيّف
and you, you have to be flexible, you have to be willing
وأنت ، عليك أن تكون مرناً ، عليك أن تكون قادراً
to change direction at a split second,
على تغيير اتجاهك في جزءٍ من الثانية ،
and she does all that. She's won this title.
إنها تفعل كل ذلك. لقد ربحت هذا اللقب.
MM: And that linking of the digital content
م.م.: وربط المحتوى الرقمي
to something that's physical is what we call an aura, and
بشيءٍ ما محسوس هو مانطلق عليه aura أو الهالة ، و
I'll be using that term a little bit as we go through the talk.
سأستخدم هذا المصطلح أثناء حديثي.
So, what's great about this is it isn't just a faster,
لذا ، الشيء الرائع هنا ليس لأنه فقط أسرع ،
more convenient way to get information in the real world,
وأكثر سهولةً للحصول على معلومات في العالم الخارجي ،
but there are times when actually using this medium
بل لأنه هناك أوقات حيث يسمح لك ذلك
allows you to be able to display information in a way
بعرض معلوماتٍ بطريقةٍ
that was never before possible.
لم تكن ممكنةً قبل الآن.
So what I have here is a wireless router.
لذا مالدي الآن هو جهاز روتر لاسلكي.
My American colleagues have told me I've got to call it a router,
نصحني صديقي الأمريكي بأن أُطلق عليه اسم راوتر ،
so that everyone here understands — (Laughter) —
لكي يفهم الجميع هنا ما أقصد -- (ضحك) --
but nonetheless, here is the device.
ماعدا ذلك ، هاهو الجهاز.
So now what I can do is, rather than getting the instructions
والآن ما أستطيع فعله ، بدلاً من قراءة التعليمات
for the device online, I can simply point at it,
للجهاز على الإنترنت ، ببساطة أُوجّه الشاشة عليه ،
the device is recognized, and then --
ويتم التعرف على الجهاز ، ومن ثم --
Voice: Begin by plugging in the grey ADSL cable.
صوت: ابدأ بتوصيل سلك ADSL الرمادي
Then connect the power. Finally, the yellow ethernet cable.
ومن ثم قم بتوصيل الكهرباء. وأخيراً ، سلك الشبكة الأصفر.
Congratulations. You have now completed setup.
مبروك. لقد أتممت للتو الإعدادات.
(Laughter) MM: Awesome. Thank you.
(ضحك) م.م.: رائع. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The incredible work that made that possible was done
والعمل الرائع الذي جعل من كل ذلك ممكناً
here in the U.K. by scientists at Cambridge,
تمّ هنا في المملكة المتحدة بواسطة علماء من كامبريدج ،
and they work in our offices,
ويعملون في مكاتبنا ،
and I've got a lovely picture of them here.
ولدي صورةً جميلةً لهم هنا.
They couldn't all be on stage, but we're going to
لم يكن بإمكانهم جميعاً الظهور على المسرح ، ولكننا
bring their aura to the stage, so here they are.
سنقدّم هالتهم هنا على المسرح ، هاهم.
They're not very animated. (Laughter)
إنهم لايتحركون كثيراً. (ضحك)
This was the fourth take, I'm told. (Laughter)
كانت هذه المحاولة الرابعة ، كما قيل لي. (ضحك)
Okay. So, as we're talking about Cambridge,
حسناً. إذاً ، بما أننا نتحدث عن كامبريدج ،
let's now move on to technical advancements,
لننتقل الآن إلى التطورات التقنية ،
because since we started putting this technology
لأننا منذ أن بدأنا بوضع هذه التقنية
on mobile phones less than 12 months ago,
على أجهزة الهاتف قبل ما يقلُ عن ١٢ شهراً ،
the speed and the processing in these devices
فإن السرعة وكمية المعالجات على هذه الأجهزة
has grown at a really phenomenal rate,
قد تطوّرت بمعدلاتٍ استثنائية ،
and that means that I can now take cinema-quality
وهذا يعني أنه بإمكاني الآن أخذ نماذج
3D models and place them in the world around me,
ثلاثية الأبعاد وبدرجة وضوح عالية ودمجها بمحيطي،
so I have one over here.
ولدي نموذجٌ هنا.
Tamara, would you like to jump in?
تمارا ، هل بإمكانك التدخّل ؟
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Dinosaur roaring) (Laughter)
(ديناصور يزئر) (ضحك)
MM: I should leap in.
م.م.: عليّ أن أقفز.
(Music) (Dinosaur roaring)
(موسيقى) (ديناصور يزئر)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So then, after the fun, comes the more emotional side
إذاً ، بعد الجانب الممتع ، يأتي الجانب الحسّي
of what we do, because effectively, this technology
لما نفعله ، لأن هذه التقنية فعلياً
allows you to see the world through someone's eyes,
تمكّنكَ من رؤية العالم من خلال شخص ٍ آخر ،
and for that person to be able to take a moment in time
وعلى ذلك الشخص أن يأخذ لحظةً من الزمن
and effectively store it and tag it to something physical
ويحفظها و يربطها بشيءٍ حِسّي
that exists in the real world.
متواجد في عالمنا الواقعي.
What's great about this is, the tools to do this are free.
والرائع في هذا ، أن الأدوات التي تمكنك من عمل ذلك مجانيةٌ.
They're open, they're available to everyone within our application,
وهي مفتوحة المصدر ، وهي بمتناول الجميع ضمن تطبيقاتنا ،
and educators have really got on board with the classrooms.
والمعلّمون بدأوا باستخدامها في الصفوف.
So we have teachers who've tagged up textbooks,
فلدينا معلّمون بالفعل ربطوا كتب دراسية ،
teachers who've tagged up school classrooms,
ومعلّمون ربطوا صفوف المدرسة ،
and a great example of this is a school in the U.K.
وكمثالٍ رائعٍ على هذا مدرسةٌ في المملكة المتحدة
I have a picture here from a video, and we're now going to play it.
لدي صورةٌ هنا من مشهد ، وسنقوم بتشغيله الآن
Teacher: See what happens. (Children talking) Keep going.
المعلم: انظروا ماذا يحدث. (أطفالٌ يتحدثون) إستمر.
Child: TV. (Children react)
طفل: تلفاز. (الأطفالُ يتفاعلون)
Child: Oh my God.
طفل: يا إلهي.
Teacher: Now move it either side. See what happens.
المعلم: والآن حرّكها على أي جانب. وراقب مايحدث.
Move away from it and come back to it.
ابتعد عنها ثم اقترب منها.
Child: Oh, that is so cool.
طفل: أوه ، هذا رائعٌ جداً.
Teacher: And then, have you got it again?
المعلم: ثم ، هل حصلت عليها مجدداً ؟
Child: Oh my God! How did you do that?
طفل: يا إلهي! كيف فعلتَ ذلك ؟
Second child: It's magic.
طفلٌ ثاني: هذا سحر.
(Laughter) MM: (Laughs) So, it's not magic.
(ضحك) م.م.: (ضحك) إذاً هذا ليس بسحر.
It's available for everyone to do,
إنه متاحٌ للجميع ،
and actually I'm going to show you how easy it is to do
وفي الواقع سأريكم سهولة عمل ذلك
by doing one right now.
بعمل ذلك الآن.
So, as sort of — I'm told it's called a stadium wave,
لذا ، كنوعٍ من -- قيل لي أن اسمه التموّج
so we're going to start from this side of the room
لذا سنبدأ من هذا الجانب من القاعة
on the count of three, and go over to here.
عند العد إلى ثلاثة ، ونتجه بهذا الإتجاه.
Tamara, are you recording?
تمارا ، هل تقومين بالتسجيل ؟
Okay, so are you all ready?
حسناً ، هل أنتم مستعدون ؟
One, two, three. Go!
واحد ، إثنين ، ثلاثة. انطلقوا!
Audience: Whooooooo!
الجمهور: ووووووووووه!
MM: Fellows are really good at that. (Laughs) (Laughter)
م.م.: الزملاء فعلاً جيدين في عمل ذلك. (ضحك)(أحدهم يضحك)
Okay. Now we're going to switch back
حسناً. والآن سنقوم بالتحويل إلى
into the Aurasma application,
برنامج عمل الهالة ،
and what Tamara's going to do is tag that video that we just
وما ستفعله تمارا هو ربط ذلك المشهد الذي التقطناه
took onto my badge, so that I can remember it forever.
ببطاقتي المعلقة ، لكي أتذكر ذلك للأبد.
Now, we have lots of people who are doing this already,
والآن هناك الكثير من الناس الذين يقومون بهذا بالفعل
and we've talked a little bit about the educational side.
وقد تحدثنا عن القليل فقط في الجانب التعليمي.
On the emotional side, we have people who've
وفي الجانب الحسي ، هناك أُناسٌ قاموا
done things like send postcards and Christmas cards
بإرسال بطاقاتٍ بريدية وبطاقات عيد الميلاد
back to their family with little messages on them.
إلى أهاليهم مع القليل من الرسائل فيها.
We have people who have, for example,
لدينا أُناسٌ ، على سبيل المثال ،
taken the inside of the engine bay of an old car
التقطوا صوراً لمكونات محرك سيارةٍ قديمة
and tagged up different components within an engine,
وربطوها بمكوناتٍ مختلفة من المحرك ،
so that if you're stuck and you want to find out more,
لذا فإذا علقت وتريد مزيداً من المعلومات ،
you can point and discover the information.
بإمكانك توجيه الشاشة والحصول على المعلومات.
We're all very, very familiar with the Internet.
إننا جميعاً معتادين جداً على الإنترنت.
In the last 20 years, it's really
في العشرين سنةً الأخيرة ، إنها بالفعل
changed the way that we live and work,
غيّرت الطريقة التي نعيش ونعمل بها ،
and the way that we see the world, and what's great is,
والطريقة التي نرى بها العالم ، والرائع في ذلك ،
we sort of think this is the next paradigm shift,
أننا نعتقد نوعاً ما أن هذه هي النقلة النوعية القادمة
because now we can literally take the content
لأنه بإمكاننا الآن أخذ المحتوى
that we share, we discover, and that we enjoy
الذي نتشاركه ، والذي نكتشفه ، والذي نستمتع به
and make it a part of the world around us.
ونجعله جزءاً من عالمنا المحيط.
It's completely free to download this application.
إن تحميل هذا البرنامج مجانيٌ تماماً.
If you have a good Wi-Fi connection or 3G,
إذا كان لديك اتصالٌ لاسلكيٌ أو خدمة 3G جيدة.
this process is very, very quick.
وهذه العملية سريعةٌ جداً جداً.
Oh, there we are. We can save it now.
أوه ، ها هي. نستطيعُ حفظها الآن.
It's just going to do a tiny bit of processing
ستقوم بعمل معالجةٍ بسيطةٍ جداً
to convert that image that we just took
لتحويل ذلك المشهد الذي التقطناه
into a sort of digital fingerprint,
إلى نوعٍ من البصمة الرقمية ،
and the great thing is, if you're a professional user,
والشيء الرائع أنه ، إذا كنت مستخدماً محترفاً ،
-- so, a newspaper -- the tools are pretty much identical
-- إذاً ، الصحيفة -- فإن الأدوات تقريباً متطابقة
to what we've just used to create this demonstration.
لما استخدمناه لعمل هذا العرض.
The only difference is that you've got the ability
والفرق الوحيد هو أنه بإمكانك
to add in links and slightly more content. Are you now ready?
إضافة روابط ومحتوياتٍ أكثر. هل أنتِ جاهزة ؟
Tamara Roukaerts: We're ready to go.
تمارا راوكيرتز: مستعدون للعرض.
MM: Okay. So, I'm told we're ready, which means
م.م.: حسناً إذاً ، قيل لي أننا مستعدون ، مما يعني
we can now point at the image, and there you all are.
أنه بإمكاننا الآن توجيه الشاشة على الصورة ، وها أنتم.
MM on video: One, two, three. Go!
م.م. في المشهد: واحد ، اثنين ، ثلاثة. انطلقوا!
MM: Well done. We've been Aurasma. Thank you.
م.م.: أحسنتم فعلاً. أصبحنا هالةً. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)